[WILLIAM] It sounds like
a delightful diversion.
Yes, and I shall
be heavily reliant
upon your insight
on this matter.
And your expertise, William.
Naturally, yes.
You did set this in motion, so
you'll take the lead, Albert.
[ALBERT] Louis, I expect
much of you, as well.
Yes, brother.
We share not only the same goal.
But also past,
present, and future.
Our lives entwined by choice.
For we three brothers
are the singular
"James Moriarty."
[SERVER 13A]
We ask you to please refrain
from speaking anyone's
name whilst inside.
Do bear in mind, this is
meant to be a masquerade ball.
Also, as part of this
evening's entertainment,
we will be playing
a riddle-solving game.
The theme of which
is the Lord of Crime.
The current talk of the town.
This mysterious
figure is rumoured
to have his hand in nearly
half of the criminal activity
that has taken place
in London of late.
The rules are simple:
one of our esteemed guests
is chosen to play
the Lord of Crime.
And that person will
commit one or more murders.
Any guest who is murdered must
reveal their face to the rest.
And then kindly
relocate to the upper floor.
Following that,
they will no longer be
able to attend the ball.
And must donate the most
costly item adorning them
towards the college
currently under construction
as a penalty for
losing the game.
Ah.
[SERVER 13A] Further,
once the remaining players
determine the
Lord of Crime's identity,
the villain will die.
And the game
will come to an end.
We shall have to do
our utmost to find them.
Yes. It sounds exhilarating.
It's my understanding
that the Yard has no clues
as to his identity so far.
Some of the common-folk
call the Lord of Crime a hero
set on bringing the dark deeds
of the upper class to light.
[NOBLEMAN 13C]
As things stand,
he is apparently as well-liked
as the Great Detective Holmes,
as a sort of symbol
representing light and darkness.
The rumour mill
is certainly churning.
Appropriate for the ruler
of London's underworld.
Bah! What rubbish!
The "Lord of Crime" indeed.
A petty criminal, getting
the Robin Hood treatment?
[ALBERT]
It's no surprise.
The noblemen who were killed
were embroiled in a
variety of scandals.
Naturally,
the townsfolk look upon
the Lord of Crime
as a valiant thief.
Hah.
It sounds like you're saying
their deaths were justified.
Very uncouth, sir.
No, nothing of the sort.
[ROLLINSON]
Who is this young chap?
Quite the disagreeable twit.
[ROLLINSON] Hmph. The fool
doesn't even realize
that I was chosen to
be the Lord of Crime.
That settles it; my very
first victim will be him.
Is something amiss, my lord?
No.
Pardon! May I have
your attention, please?
Regarding tonight's
game of intrigue,
our Lord of Crime's
first heinous act
has already been committed.
The fiend's first victim will
be marked with red wine.
Anyone who has had wine
splashed on them
has been murdered.
Take this time to
inspect those around you.
Did he say wine?
I've survived thus far,
it would seem.
Would you be so kind
as to check my back?
[NOBLEWOMAN 13A gasps]
Oh, dear!
Well, it would appear that
I am the killer's first victim.
[NOBLEWOMAN 13C]
Not Lord Moriarty!
[NOBLEWOMAN 13D]
Who would splash wine on
such a fine young man?
I was Earl Albert James
Moriarty, before my death!
[NOBLEWOMAN 13E]
No! Lord Moriarty!
Ah, yes, that's right.
I shall be donating this ring.
[SERVER 13A] Thank you, my lord.
Such a generous offering.
[ROLLINSON] I never expected
someone so young to be an earl.
Ladies and gentlemen,
a round of applause
for His Lordship!
[CROWD clapping, cheers]
[ADLER]
I, as well.
Huh?
It would appear that I, too,
have fallen victim
to the Lord of Crime!
[ROLLINSON grunts]
[ROLLINSON] I don't recall
splashing any on him.
Rather clever of you to adopt
a second persona to
come here tonight,
Miss Irene Adler.
You could have taken me
into your custody
when you bumped into
me at Baker Street.
The fact that you didn't,
shows that you have no wish
to deal roughly with me.
And now, thanks to you
arranging this anonymous affair,
I feel you can be trusted--
someone with whom
I could negotiate.
How very judicious.
I have been charged
with the task
of handling this matter
by the government.
You may freely take my word
to be the very word of
the British authority itself.
The papers you stole
from the palace--
you are willing to
return them to us?
With pleasure, though,
I have some conditions.
Firstly, you must guarantee
my safety from reprisals.
Secondly, the government must
overlook the crime of my theft.
If you will observe
these two conditions,
I will return them at once.
[ALBERT] My answer, on behalf
of the government is no.
[ADLER gasps]
My superiors have afforded me no
room to bargain in this matter.
The orders I was issued were to
seize the documents and
then to liquidate you.
Why did you summon me here
if that was your purpose?
Whilst I serve as an
agent of the government,
it was not in that capacity
that I called on you.
[ADLER gasps]
[ALBERT] I had my
reservations from the outset.
Why did the thief
who stole the documents
choose to do nothing with them?
She gave no demands,
nor did she claim
responsibility for the theft.
Why would that be?
Perhaps because
she realised that
the content of the papers was
beyond what she could handle.
And was desperate to find a
safer means of returning them.
But now, it is
no longer possible
to cast aside the
prospect that
you have learnt some dirty state
secret.
Overlooking your crime and
guaranteeing your safety
in the light of this new
information would be impossible.
If that's true, you've only
come here to inform me directly
- -that I have no hope of any--
- -[ALBERT] No, you're wrong.
- -What?
[ALBERT] I'm here because I just
may have a way to save you.
You'll "save" me?
What do you mean?
[ALBERT] However, my offer is
entirely dependent
on how critical the content of
those papers is to the nation.
[ADLER gasps]
But if you knew,
you would be placed
in the same position
that I've found myself in.
No matter, I can deal
with that problem
once I know what
those papers contain.
I promise you--
you'll regret hearing
what I'm about to tell you.
[ALBERT gasps]
[ADLER grunts]
[ALBERT chuckles]
[ALBERT cackling]
[ALBERT]
It's not about the royal family.
This scandal concerns the entire
British Empire, doesn't it?
And you truly believe you
have the ability to save me?
[ALBERT chuckles]
But of course.
I'm able to save you, and more.
Would you care for a sample?
[ALBERT] Just look at
that man in the white mask.
That is Baron Ronald Rollinson.
The Lord of Crime for
tonight's entertainment.
How do you know that?
Because I am one of the hosts
of this evening's festivities.
But that isn't my point.
The Baron operates opera houses
in both America and France.
His personality is
cruel and self-serving.
Five years ago, he set
fire to one of his theatres.
He made it look
like an accident,
for the insurance money,
killing many of
the people inside.
What? I know all
about that fire.
Some of my friends were
killed in the blaze.
You're telling me
that man's responsible?
[ALBERT]
It's time.
Watch carefully now.
[SERVER 13A]
Attention!
Our Lord of Crime has
been caught at last!
Our villain tonight
has been Baron Ronald Rollinson!
[CROWD claps]
[SERVER 13A]
The Lord of Crime is dead,
and peace returns to
the great city of London!
You are all the winners!
I didn't know it
was you, old boy!
[ROLLINSON wheezes, groans]
Are you all right?
You're looking a bit pale.
[ROLLINSON groaning]
- -[ADLER grunts]
- -[NOBLEMAN 13A] Hamming it up?
[NOBLEMAN 13A]
You can stop acting already.
[ROLLINSON]
C-Can't breathe.
[ROLLINSON groans]
[ADLER gasps]
- -[heart thumps]
- -[ROLLINSON wheezes]
- -[NOBLEWOMAN 13C] Oh!
- -[NOBLEWOMAN 13D] No.
[NOBLEMAN 13E]
How dreadful. He looks ghastly!
[NOBLEMAN 13A]
He isn't breathing.
[NOBLEMAN 13C]
Baron? Baron!
Answer me! Hey!
Someone call a doctor!
[ALBERT] His performance--
what'd you think?
[ALBERT]
Baron Rollinson played his part
as the main
character exquisitely.
As did the other nobles
who met their demise.
And now I have pronounced
the same punishment on him.
[ADLER]
It can't be...
Unless he's...
Yes, I set this entire
scene in motion, Miss Adler.
The Lord of Crime, James
Moriarty, at your service.
Dear God, you are him.
Have a look.
[ALBERT]
Even when a man dies,
the aristocracy
continues their party
without a second thought.
Because the fools are
only interested in themselves.
Which means,
no matter how many aristocrats
get killed like this,
there is no changing them.
Aristocracy doesn't refer to
the finely-dressed
people themselves,
but to the very
concept they embody.
[ALBERT] That said, no man can
kill an intangible concept.
Your objective is the
same as mine, is it not?
[ADLER gasps]
My objective is clear:
to fundamentally change
this nation at its core,
to move it from a society
based on right of blood
to a free society
based on merit.
The methodology I use
to bring about reform
in this twisted world
is organized crime.
Just as you yourself
resort to theft,
extortion, and other
crimes as your methods.
[ADLER] Changing the
world through crime.
Maybe he's not so mad after all.
Please forgive me for
speaking at such length.
I will be waiting for you
in the church along
New North Road in Hoxton
just before dawn.
At this point,
you have run out of both
time and further options.
It is my hope you
will choose wisely.
[ADLER]
Lord Albert James Moriarty.
[ADLER] So, the Lord of Crime is
a nobleman who's worked his way
into the heart of the
government, at that.
But the question remains:
does he really have the
power to change anything?
[ADLER gasps]
- -[whip snaps]
- -[HORSES clopping]
[ADLER] First, I need to get the
papers
without Sherlock and the others
noticing.
[ADLER grunting]
My God!
[ADLER gasps]
No.
[ADLER]
Sherlock!
I-Irene, hurry!
He wanted us to hand you over.
I said I didn't know you
and told him to get out of here.
He had the moves of someone
who was extremely well trained
and it took all we
had to turn him back.
I can't believe we didn't
see him plant the bomb.
I'd have sworn he
was only bluffing,
but he meant business.
[groans]
[HOLMES]
You have to--
You have to get out of here.
I couldn't!
You must!
[ADLER grunts]
[ADLER] It's all my fault
they got dragged into this.
I can't let anything
else awful happen to them!
[gasps]
I see.
Thank you for showing me
where you've been hiding it.
Why, Sherlock.
I thought that you--
It worked this time, Irene.
At last, I've won.
[ADLER grunts]
[WATSON]
Honestly,
blowing up the second floor
solely to trick Miss Adler.
I thought you were mad
when you first proposed it,
but it seems to have worked!
And Miss Hudson's
performance was stellar.
Well, after the two
of you blew up my home,
I wasn't about to mess that up!
You... set this up?
To go this far. Why?
It's simple.
Because we wanted to
protect you, Miss Adler.
Protect? How so?
[HOLMES] I knew there was
something else motivating you
aside from the photo
of the King of Bohemia.
Which implied that the king's
request was meaningless.
It stood to reason that the
king's photo was a red herring.
Which would mean, your real
objective
was to work your way close to
me.
Which seemed unfathomable at
first.
Foregoing my powers
of deduction,
as much as I hate to say it,
my current level of popularity
is what you found most useful.
Someone will find it
difficult to move against you,
while you're in the orbit
of one of London's
most famous citizens.
Which suggests, whoever
is coming for you--
they aren't the mafia
or the nobility,
who would stop at nothing
to deal with the matter.
So, why is the British
government out to get you?
Hoping to bring that
reason to light,
we pretended to
come under attack,
and you fell for it.
Now, what could this be?
Stop, Sherlock!
If you look,
there's no going back!
They're just going to come after
you, like they came for me!
Hah. I destroyed my own room
to get my hands on this secret.
You think I'm concerned
about who might come after me?
[LOUIS]
I'm sorry, tactical plans?
[ALBERT] Yes. 100 years ago,
the British Empire,
had a hand in manipulating
the French Revolution
from the shadows.
Those were the plans for it.
What? Why was there
a need for that?
[WILLIAM]
It's quite simple, Louis.
It was an experiment.
The purpose of which was
to see what would happen
if an oppressive monarchy
were to switch to
a republic of the common man.
Well,
it's possible the British
government's plan had always
been intended to trigger a
bloody revolution of some sort.
It would at least throw
the ensuing French government
into a cascading
state of turmoil.
Whatever the case,
it seems, we must retrieve
those papers post-haste.
From this moment on,
there's no turning back for us.
How the devil did
you get your hands on
a document this dangerous?
I might have stolen it
from Buckingham Palace.
Though I never would have taken
it if I knew what was inside.
I just needed something in
order to blackmail the prince,
that's all.
[WATSON grunts] You intended
to blackmail the prince?
To what end, exactly?
[ADLER]
My goal was to reform the world.
It's what I have always done.
It started when an actress
I knew was driven to
take her own life simply because
she was from a common family.
No matter how hard she worked,
she was never given her due.
I urged the nobility, who had
been criticising her so cruelly,
to see things in
a different light.
I used my feminine allure to
ingratiate myself into
their circle, and from there,
exploited the upper
class's weaknesses.
And so, I supported those who
would not have moved ahead
due to their social status.
I worked to ensure
that their talents
would one day bear fruit.
You expect us to believe
you did something
that grand by yourself?
[HOLMES]
No, John. It's the truth.
Having heard this my profile
of Miss Adler finally fits.
With leverage on the prince,
I had a chance to
change this country.
But instead, I stole something
too big for me to handle.
I'm a fool.
And then I dragged all
of you into this, as well.
I'm sorry.
That's just bad luck.
So, care to tell us where
you've been all evening?
[ADLER] The government
promised to spare me...
...on the condition
that I turn over the papers
you're currently holding.
As well as all the
information I've obtained.
Don't you see? Without that
folder, my life is over!
Sherlock, please.
[HOLMES grunts]
Are you sure about
this, Sherlock?
Giving her the pages?
[HOLMES groans]
That's it! I've
had enough of this!
[groans] Our options
are running thin and yet,
what she said is clearly untrue!
[WATSON gasps]
What are you on about?
What Irene said about reasoning
with the government was untrue.
I said it before.
The government--no, he  has never
been one to do things so simply.
Which means our
con-artist courtesan
is dealing with someone else!
Really? But who could it be?
[HOLMES]
Elementary, my dear Watson.
Who would want such
a godforsaken document
and have enough
influence to protect Irene
from the clutches
of the government?
Yes, Irene has made a deal with
the Lord of Crime.
[LOUIS] Next time on
Moriarty the Patriot  :
"A Scandal in the
British Empire Act 3."